{"mainPropery":{"diseaseId":5700,"diseaseName":"Rickets","hasGardWebPage":true,"isRare":true,"websiteUrl":"https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/5700/rickets","synonyms":["Vitamin-D deficiency rickets","Nutritional rickets","Hypovitaminosis D","Vitamin D deficiency disease"],"synonyms-with-source":[{"name":"Vitamin-D deficiency rickets"},{"name":"Nutritional rickets"},{"name":"Hypovitaminosis D"},{"name":"Vitamin D deficiency disease"}],"identifiers":[]},"diseaseCategories":[{"diseaseTypeId":18,"diseaseTypeName":"Nutritional diseases"}],"organizations":[],"resource descriptions":[{"id":8,"resourceId":11,"resourceName":"PubMed","descriptionText":"<a href='http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?Db=pubmed&Cmd=DetailsSearch&Term=((%22rickets%22%5BMeSH+Terms%5D+OR+rickets%5BText+Word%5D)+AND+(%22vitamin+d%22%5BMeSH+Terms%5D+OR+%22ergocalciferols%22%5BMeSH+Terms%5D+OR+vitamin+d%5BText+Word%5D))+AND+(hasabstract%5Btext%5D+AND+%222005%2F04%2F16%22%5BEDat%5D+%3A+%222008%2F04%2F14%22%5BEDat%5D+AND+%22humans%22%5BMeSH+Terms%5D+AND+English%5Blang%5D)' target='_blank'>PubMed</a> is a searchable database of medical literature and lists journal articles that discuss Rickets. Click on the link to view a sample search on this topic.","resourceClassificationName":"Overview","resourceClassificationSectionName":"In-Depth Information"},{"id":9,"resourceId":12,"resourceName":"ClinicalTrials.gov","descriptionText":"<a href='http://www.clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?cond=%22Rickets%22' target='_blank'>ClinicalTrials.gov</a> lists trials that are related to Rickets. Click on the link to go to ClinicalTrials.gov to read descriptions of these studies. <br />\r\n<br />\r\n<em><strong>Please note:</strong>&nbsp;Studies listed on the&nbsp;ClinicalTrials.gov&nbsp;website are listed for informational purposes only; being listed does not reflect an endorsement by GARD or the NIH. We strongly recommend that you talk with a trusted healthcare provider before choosing to participate in any clinical study.</em>","resourceClassificationName":"Research","resourceClassificationSectionName":"Clinical Research Resources"},{"id":10,"resourceId":13,"resourceName":"MedlinePlus Genetics","descriptionText":"<a href='http://ghr.nlm.nih.gov/condition/vitamin-d-dependent-rickets' target='_blank'>Genetics Home Reference (GHR)</a> contains information on Rickets. This website is maintained by the National Library of Medicine.<br />\r\n","resourceClassificationName":"Overview","resourceClassificationSectionName":"Where to Start"},{"id":1401,"resourceId":2052,"resourceName":"Office of Dietary Supplements","descriptionText":"<a href='http://ods.od.nih.gov/factsheets/vitamind.asp ' target='_blank'>The Office of Dietary Supplements</a> provides more information on vitamin D. You can view this information by clicking on the Office of Dietary Supplements link.","resourceClassificationName":"Overview","resourceClassificationSectionName":"Where to Start"},{"id":1529,"resourceId":2128,"resourceName":"MedlinePlus","descriptionText":"<a href='http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/rickets.html' target='_blank'>MedlinePlus</a> was designed by the National Library of Medicine to help you research your health questions, and it provides more information about this topic.\r\n<br />\r\n","resourceClassificationName":"Overview","resourceClassificationSectionName":"Where to Start"},{"id":1531,"resourceId":2162,"resourceName":"Medscape Reference","descriptionText":"<a href='http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/985510-overview' target='_blank'>Medscape Reference</a> provides information on this topic. You may need to register to view the medical textbook, but registration is free.<br />\r\n","resourceClassificationName":"Overview","resourceClassificationSectionName":"In-Depth Information"},{"id":2135,"resourceId":3342,"resourceName":"Monarch Initiative","descriptionText":"The <a href='https://monarchinitiative.org/disease/DOID:10609' target='_blank'>Monarch Initiative</a> brings together data about this condition from humans and other species to help physicians and biomedical researchers. Monarch&rsquo;s tools are designed to make it easier to compare the signs and symptoms (phenotypes) of different diseases and discover common features. This initiative is a collaboration between several academic institutions across the world and is funded by the National Institutes of Health. Visit the website to explore the biology of this condition.","resourceClassificationName":"Overview","resourceClassificationSectionName":"In-Depth Information"}],"overviewQuestion":{"questionId":513,"questionText":"What is rickets?","answerText":"<strong>Rickets</strong> is a condition that causes children to have soft, weak bones. It usually occurs when children do not get enough <a href=\"http://ods.od.nih.gov/factsheets/vitamind.asp\" target=_blank>vitamin D</a>, which helps growing bones absorb important nutrients. Vitamin D comes from sunlight and food. Skin produces vitamin D in response to the sun's rays. Some foods also contain vitamin D, including fortified dairy products and cereals, and some kinds of fish.[342]","dateModified":"2013-07-26T13:29:00"},"basicQuestions":[{"questionId":514,"questionText":"What are the signs and symptoms of rickets?","answerText":"The signs and symptoms of rickets include:[344][345] \r\n<ul>\r\n<li>Bone pain or tenderness \r\n<li>Bowed (curved) legs \r\n<li>Large forehead \r\n<li>Stunted growth \r\n<li>Abnormally curved spine \r\n<li>Large abdomen \r\n<li>Abnormally shaped ribs and breastbone \r\n<li>Wide wrist and elbow joints \r\n<li>Teeth abnormalities</li></ul>","dateModified":"2013-07-26T13:31:00","resourceClassificationName":"Symptoms","references":[{"referenceId":344,"authors":"Van Voorhees BW","articleTitle":"Rickets","bookWebsiteJournalTitle":"MedlinePlus Web site","date":"August 18, 2008","url":"http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000344.htm","dateAccessed":"2008-04-14T00:00:00"},{"referenceId":345,"authors":"","articleTitle":"Rickets: What It Is and How It's Treated","bookWebsiteJournalTitle":"FamilyDoctor.org","date":"September 2007","url":"http://familydoctor.org/online/famdocen/home/children/parents/special/bone/902.printerview.html","dateAccessed":"2008-04-14T00:00:00"}]},{"questionId":517,"questionText":"What causes rickets?","answerText":"Rickets is caused by a lack of vitamin D. A child might not get enough vitamin D if he or she:[342] \r\n<li>Has dark skin \r\n<li>Spends too little time outside \r\n<li>Has on sunscreen all the time when out of doors \r\n<li>Doesn't eat foods containing vitamin D because of lactose intolerance or a strict vegetarian diet \r\n<li>Is breastfed without receiving vitamin D supplements \r\n<li>Can't make or use vitamin D because of a medical disorder such as celiac disease \r\n<li>Has an inherited disorder that affects vitamin D levels</li>","dateModified":"2013-07-26T13:34:00","resourceClassificationName":"Cause","references":[{"referenceId":342,"authors":"","articleTitle":"Rickets","bookWebsiteJournalTitle":"MedlinePlus Web site","date":"September 9, 2007","url":"http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/rickets.html","dateAccessed":"2008-04-14T00:00:00"}]},{"questionId":515,"questionText":"How is rickets diagnosed?","answerText":"Rickets is typically diagnosed using specific blood tests and x-rays. Blood tests usually show low levels of calcium and phosphorus and high levels of alkaline phosphatase. Bone x-rays may show areas with calcium loss or changes in bone shape. Bone biopsies are rarely performed, but can confirm the diagnosis of rickets.[344]","dateModified":"2013-07-26T13:32:00","resourceClassificationName":"Diagnosis","references":[{"referenceId":344,"authors":"Van Voorhees BW","articleTitle":"Rickets","bookWebsiteJournalTitle":"MedlinePlus Web site","date":"August 18, 2008","url":"http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000344.htm","dateAccessed":"2008-04-14T00:00:00"}]},{"questionId":518,"questionText":"What treatment is available for rickets?","answerText":"The treatment for rickets depends on the cause of the condition. If rickets is caused by a lack of vitamin D in the diet, then it is usually treated with carefully adjusted levels of vitamin D and calcium. The child's condition may improve within a few weeks of treatment. If rickets is caused by an inherited disorder or another medical condition, a healthcare provider would determine the appropriate treatment.[345]","dateModified":"2013-07-26T13:35:00","resourceClassificationName":"Treatment","references":[{"referenceId":345,"authors":"","articleTitle":"Rickets: What It Is and How It's Treated","bookWebsiteJournalTitle":"FamilyDoctor.org","date":"September 2007","url":"http://familydoctor.org/online/famdocen/home/children/parents/special/bone/902.printerview.html","dateAccessed":"2008-04-14T00:00:00"}]}],"references":[],"relatedDiseases":[{"relatedDiseaseId":12942,"relatedDiseaseName":"Hypophosphatemic","relation":"Child","isRare":true,"hasGardPage":true}],"gardCases":[{"caseId":21455,"abbreviatedInquiry":"My baby has been diagnosed with vitamin D deficiency. He has also been found to have high levels of parathyroid hormone and alkaline phosphatase.&nbsp;An x-ray examination did not show any signs of rickets. Is it true that babies younger than 6 months may not have signs of rickets on x-ray? I would like to learn as much as possible about rickets, including how it is diagnosed.","caseQuestions":[{"questionId":513,"questionText":"What is rickets?","answerText":"<strong>Rickets</strong> is a condition that causes children to have soft, weak bones. It usually occurs when children do not get enough <a href=\"http://ods.od.nih.gov/factsheets/vitamind.asp\" target=_blank>vitamin D</a>, which helps growing bones absorb important nutrients. Vitamin D comes from sunlight and food. Skin produces vitamin D in response to the sun's rays. Some foods also contain vitamin D, including fortified dairy products and cereals, and some kinds of fish.[342]","dateModified":"2013-07-26T13:29:00","references":[{"referenceId":342,"authors":"","articleTitle":"Rickets","bookWebsiteJournalTitle":"MedlinePlus Web site","date":"September 9, 2007","url":"http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/rickets.html","dateAccessed":"2008-04-14T00:00:00"}]},{"questionId":514,"questionText":"What are the signs and symptoms of rickets?","answerText":"The signs and symptoms of rickets include:[344][345] \r\n<ul>\r\n<li>Bone pain or tenderness \r\n<li>Bowed (curved) legs \r\n<li>Large forehead \r\n<li>Stunted growth \r\n<li>Abnormally curved spine \r\n<li>Large abdomen \r\n<li>Abnormally shaped ribs and breastbone \r\n<li>Wide wrist and elbow joints \r\n<li>Teeth abnormalities</li></ul>","dateModified":"2013-07-26T13:31:00","resourceClassificationName":"Symptoms","references":[{"referenceId":344,"authors":"Van Voorhees BW","articleTitle":"Rickets","bookWebsiteJournalTitle":"MedlinePlus Web site","date":"August 18, 2008","url":"http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000344.htm","dateAccessed":"2008-04-14T00:00:00"},{"referenceId":345,"authors":"","articleTitle":"Rickets: What It Is and How It's Treated","bookWebsiteJournalTitle":"FamilyDoctor.org","date":"September 2007","url":"http://familydoctor.org/online/famdocen/home/children/parents/special/bone/902.printerview.html","dateAccessed":"2008-04-14T00:00:00"}]},{"questionId":515,"questionText":"How is rickets diagnosed?","answerText":"Rickets is typically diagnosed using specific blood tests and x-rays. Blood tests usually show low levels of calcium and phosphorus and high levels of alkaline phosphatase. Bone x-rays may show areas with calcium loss or changes in bone shape. Bone biopsies are rarely performed, but can confirm the diagnosis of rickets.[344]","dateModified":"2013-07-26T13:32:00","resourceClassificationName":"Diagnosis","references":[{"referenceId":344,"authors":"Van Voorhees BW","articleTitle":"Rickets","bookWebsiteJournalTitle":"MedlinePlus Web site","date":"August 18, 2008","url":"http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000344.htm","dateAccessed":"2008-04-14T00:00:00"}]},{"questionId":516,"questionText":"Is it true that babies younger than 6 months of age may not have signs of rickets on x-ray?","answerText":"X-rays may not be able to diagnose rickets during the early stages of this condition; however, chemical changes in the blood would already be present. Although x-rays of both the wrist and knee are commonly used to diagnose rickets, knee x-rays may be more reliable for infants.[343]","dateModified":"2013-07-26T13:33:00","resourceClassificationName":"Symptoms","references":[{"referenceId":343,"authors":"van Rijn RR, McHugh K","articleTitle":"Rickets","bookWebsiteJournalTitle":"eMedicine Web site","date":"Feb 2, 2007","url":"http://www.emedicine.com/radio/TOPIC610.HTM","dateAccessed":"2008-04-14T00:00:00"}]},{"questionId":517,"questionText":"What causes rickets?","answerText":"Rickets is caused by a lack of vitamin D. A child might not get enough vitamin D if he or she:[342] \r\n<li>Has dark skin \r\n<li>Spends too little time outside \r\n<li>Has on sunscreen all the time when out of doors \r\n<li>Doesn't eat foods containing vitamin D because of lactose intolerance or a strict vegetarian diet \r\n<li>Is breastfed without receiving vitamin D supplements \r\n<li>Can't make or use vitamin D because of a medical disorder such as celiac disease \r\n<li>Has an inherited disorder that affects vitamin D levels</li>","dateModified":"2013-07-26T13:34:00","resourceClassificationName":"Cause","references":[{"referenceId":342,"authors":"","articleTitle":"Rickets","bookWebsiteJournalTitle":"MedlinePlus Web site","date":"September 9, 2007","url":"http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/rickets.html","dateAccessed":"2008-04-14T00:00:00"}]},{"questionId":518,"questionText":"What treatment is available for rickets?","answerText":"The treatment for rickets depends on the cause of the condition. If rickets is caused by a lack of vitamin D in the diet, then it is usually treated with carefully adjusted levels of vitamin D and calcium. The child's condition may improve within a few weeks of treatment. If rickets is caused by an inherited disorder or another medical condition, a healthcare provider would determine the appropriate treatment.[345]","dateModified":"2013-07-26T13:35:00","resourceClassificationName":"Treatment","references":[{"referenceId":345,"authors":"","articleTitle":"Rickets: What It Is and How It's Treated","bookWebsiteJournalTitle":"FamilyDoctor.org","date":"September 2007","url":"http://familydoctor.org/online/famdocen/home/children/parents/special/bone/902.printerview.html","dateAccessed":"2008-04-14T00:00:00"}]}]}],"news":[{"newsId":671,"dateCreated":"2020-05-20T13:39:00","publishDate":"2020-05-22T00:00:00","title":"NIH-Supported Research Survey to Examine Impact of COVID-19 on Rare Diseases Community","description":"The NIH-funded Rare Diseases Clinical Research Network (RDCRN) has launched an <a href=\"https://www.rarediseasesnetwork.org/COVIDsurvey \" target=\"_blank\">online research survey</a> to find out how the COVID-19 pandemic is impacting individuals with rare diseases, their families and their caregivers. Your participation can help the rare disease research community shed light on the needs of people with rare diseases during this and other potential health crises, in addition to informing future research efforts. The survey must be completed by December 15, 2020.","url":"https://www.rarediseasesnetwork.org/COVIDsurvey","lastModified":"2020-11-30T14:44:00","isFeatured":false}],"conferences":[],"phenoTypes":[],"medicalProducts":[],"EncodedName":"Rickets"}